Guide to the Helen I. Breed papers, 1947-1992.
Breed, Helen I. papers, 1947-1992.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Helen I. Breed papers, 1947-1992.
21-18-3415
Helen Illick Breed, 1925-2001.
6 cubic ft.
Student papers and research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes student papers and research materials for Hellen I. Breed's doctoral dissertation.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Helen Josephine Illick received her bachelor's (1947) and master's (1949) degrees from Syracuse University. She received a Ph.D. from Cornell University in 1953, and served as a research associate in the Department of Natural Resources with Edward Raney.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Student papers and research materials for her doctoral dissertation: A comparative study of the lateral-line system on the head of North American Cyprinidae, 1953; research notes, including Lake George research files; photographs and slides relating to her research on Cyprinidae (carps and minnows) family and the genus Hybopsis (chubs); laboratory slides; specimen ledger; bibliography cards; materials on the Rensselaer County Environmental Council; and materials on the 1992 United Nations "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Also, correspondence files from 1954 through 1969/70, including consistent correspondence with Edward Raney; about 3 years of correspondence on her Earth Summit activity; and 2001 Woman of Distinction poster for Dr. Breed.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Breed, Helen Illick, 1925-2001.; Raney, Edward C. (Edward Cowden), 1909-; New York State College of Agriculture. Department of Natural Resources.; United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (1992: Rio de Janeiro, Brazil)
Subjects:
Ichthyology.; Cyprinidae.; Hybopsis.; Ichthyologists.; Women scientists--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Master of Zoology Thesis-Syracuse University, June 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Paper- Factors Influencing Lapillary Permeability (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Paper- Generalized Description of Cephalic Lateral-Line Canals of the Cyprinidae (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ceph. Lat. Line Canals of Cyprinidae - Notes, Outlines, Drafts, Glass Plates (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ceph. Lat. Line Canals of Cyprinidae - Figures, Plates (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ceph. Lat. Line Canals of Cyprinidae - Notes by Edward C. Raney, Cornell University, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ceph. Lat. Line Canals of Cyprinidae -Draft (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Doctoral Thesis (Draft) - Cornell University - Comp of Lat. Line of Cyprinidae, Sept. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Graduate Work - Water Metabolism in Mice - Lab Notes, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Use of Tape Recording in Conservation Education - Correspondenc, Pamphlets, Clippings, and Meeting Notes (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bound AA's in Muscles of Fishes (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Reprints - X-Ray Diffraction Studies of Hard Tissues of Verts. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bound AA's in Muscles of Fishes - Complete Copy - Notes by E.C. Raney, May 5, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bound AA's in Muscles of Fishes -Chromatography Manuscript Draft 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bound AA's in Muscles of Fishes - Discussion - Copy 4 and carbon copy (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Chromatographic and Lab Data Sheets - Norwegian Fishes (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Annual Report European Research, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Chromatography Reprints (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Chromatography Laboratory Equipment (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ceph. Lat. Line Canals - Rough Drafts and Original of Paper (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notropis baileyi, N. chrosomus, N. lutipinnis (lat. line) - Reprints and Original (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bound AA's Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Copies of X-Ray Diffraction Proposal and Preparation of Tissues (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Research Grant Requests (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Hard Tissue Research (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Chromatography Lab Data (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Archival Copy - Cyprinidae (I-V) - Ceph. Lat. Line Diagrams - Natural Res., Cornell (Box 1, Folder 28-32)
- Research Materials (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Hybopsis Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hybopsis Pictures (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
- Hybopsis Slides (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Notebook 1, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
- Notebook 2 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
- Notebook 3 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Notebook 4, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Lake George (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Lake George - NYS Conservation Dept. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Lake George - Research Proposal, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Lake George - Proposal - Physics Dept. RPI, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Lake George - Research Proposal - Drafts and Carbons (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Lake George - Study (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Lake George - Reprints (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
- Rensselaer County Environmental Managment Council (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Exxon Environmental Publications (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Science, Aug.-Sept. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Lab Manual for Mammalian Physiology (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Articles - Women in Science (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Newsletters and Reports (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Appointment to RCEMC, 1971, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Environmental Council - Dr. Helen I. Breed (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Environmental Reports (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Fisheries Newsletters, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Traveling Expense Vouchers (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Speech - Tamarac High School Graduation, June 25, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Newspaper Clippings (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence - Obstruction of Indian Creek Rd. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- International Council on Metals and the Environment (Box 3, Folder 17)
- UN - High-Level Advisory Board on Sustainable Development (Box 3, Folder 18)
- The '92 Global Forum, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (Box 3, Folder 19)
- UNCED Preparatory Committee (Prep Com IV) (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Critiques - Prep Com IV Documents bases on Women's Action Agenda 21 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Press Releases - Rio and Environmental (Box 3, Folder 22)
- United Nations Press Releases (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Ad Hoc Discussion Group - BCERF, February 5, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- UNCED - Agenda 21 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Carnegie Council Environmental Seminar, February 24, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Council on Foreign Relations - Global Warming, April 2, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Bella Abzug Memorial Service (Box 3, Folder 28)
- WEDO and WIPAC (Box 3, Folder 29)
- World Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet - Action 21 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Correspondence - Bella Abzug - WEDO, WIPAC (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Alicia Barcena - Earth Council (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Woman's Caucus, March 1992 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Environment (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Nicholas Robinson (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Chief Bisi Ogunleye - Africa - Local Initiative: Key to Women's Voice in Global Decision Making (Box 3, Folder 36)
- International Organizations - Earth Council, Center for Common Future, etc. (Box 3, Folder 37)
- A World Congress for Education and Communication on Environment and Development - Toronto, Canada, October 17-21, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Eastman Kodak Chemical Co. "Responsible Care" Member (Box 3, Folder 39)
- United Earth and Earth Prize Awards (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Dunlap, Riley E. "American Environmentalism" (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Gallop - "The Health of the Planet Survey" (Box 3, Folder 42)
- From Rio to the Capitols - State Strategies for Sustainable Development, May 1993 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Professional Reports A-C (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Professional Reports D-E (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Professional Reports G-H (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Professional Reports L-M (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Professional Reports N-P (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Professional Reports R-S (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Professional Reports T-U (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Professional Reports W (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Carbohydrate Metabolism (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Steroids from the Adrenal Cortex (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Laboratory Examination - Muscles (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Hour Examination - Skeleton and Muscle (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Hour Examination - Nervous System (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Hour Examination - Circulation (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Respiration Exam (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Outhine - Previous Course at RS (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Physiology 202 - Final Exam (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Physiology 106A - Final Exam (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Outline of Lectures and Laboratories for Anatomy and Physiology (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Lecture Notes - Human Physiology 136 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Vertebrate Paleontology (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Ichthyology Lectures (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Nature Writings (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Endocrinology - Final Exam (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Physiology 105A - Final Exam (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Lecture Notes - Physiology, 105B (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Physiology 105 - Exam (Box 4, Folder 19)
- State University Teachers' College (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Examinations - Physiology 105 - Vassar (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Examinations - Physiology 91 and 136 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Tissues (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Junior College of Russell Sage College (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Physiology 105A - Tentative Outline for 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Introduction for the Student (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Lab Outlines - 1st Semester - Biology 105B (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Physiology 91- Laboratory Experiments (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Biology - Laboratory Outlines (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Zoology I - Outline (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Russell Sage Quill (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Botany - Lab Outline (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Geology - Textbook (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Conservation - Classroom Material (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Histology and Cytolgoy - Lecture Notes, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Entomology - Lecture Notes, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Vertebrate Anatomy - Lab Guide and Exam Booklet (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Geology - Lecture Outline (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Mammology - Lecture Notes (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Ornithology - Lecture Notes (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Economic Zoology (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Botany - Lecture Notes and Lab Outlines, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- General Education - National Science - Class Materials (Box 4, Folder 43)
- General Science - Lecture Notes, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Entomology (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Bibliography Cards I (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Bibliography Cards II (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Bibliography Cards III (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Bibliography Cards IV (Box 4, Folder 49)
- 3 Metal Boxes of Bibliography Cards (Box 5)
- 5 Wooden Boxes Fixed Microscope Slides - Histology (Box 5)
- Red Wooden Box Fixed Microscope Slides - Various (Box 5)
- 3 Metal Boxes Transparency Slides (Box 5)
- Record of Specimens used in Chromatography Studies of Fishes (Box 5)
- NYS program, Rio, etc., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Letters of recommendation and invitation, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Governor Mario Cuomo, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Dr. Martin Smith - NiMo [Niagara-Mohawk] Environmental Affairs, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Joseph Martens, Deputy Secretary to the Governor, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - Langdon Marsh, Executive Deputy Commissioner N.Y.S. Environmental Conservation, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence - Maurice Hinchey, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- N.Y.S. Environmental Summit, Rye, N.Y., 12/2-12/4/1992, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Rio/etc., 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Notes, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence - Henry Eltinge Breed III [son], 1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- WEDO [Women's Environment and Development Organization] Comments, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Economic Impact, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Rensselaer Health Department, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Resources study, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- RPI [Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute] publications, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Environmental Conservation Commission, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Environmental publications, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Publications, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Biological Congress News, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Alumni newsletter, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Publications, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Scientific Collecting, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Summer 1966 Appointment: Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Business correspondence, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Letter of Appointment R.P.I., 1964 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Correspondence, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- AIBS [American Institute of Biological Sciences] Bulletin, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- N.S.F., 1957 (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Publications, 1956, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Correspondence, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Position offers and letters of acceptance for teaching or research, 1946-1957 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Graduate School, 1946-1953 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Vita and Personal Credentials, 1952-1956 (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Biology, General Science, Hygiene Class: Quizzes and Exams, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- The Log, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Correspondence, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Manual for an Introduction to Geology, by Robert O. Bloomer, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Additional material (Box 7)
- Posters of forums and events, etc (Folder 1)
- Photocopies of newspaper clippings and other material on Joseph S. Illick and Hellen J. Illick; Helen J. Illick paper on Anna Botsford Comstock, 1952-1992 (Folder 1)